George Crumb Papers
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
George Crumb Papers1956-2011 (bulk 1965-2003)
ML31.C87
Crumb, George
approximately 6,300 items 35 containers 25.0 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
George Crumb is a Pulitzer Prize-winning American composer, long-associated with the University of Pennsylvania. The collection consists of holograph manuscript scores and sketches, correspondence, business papers, and a series of meticulously assembled scrapbooks chronicling Crumb's career as a composer.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Burge, David, 1930- --Correspondence.; Crumb, George--Archives.; Crumb, George--Correspondence.; Crumb, George--Manuscripts.; Crumb, George--Performances.; Crumb, George--Photographs.; Crumb, George.; Crumb, George.; Crumb, George. Selections.
Organizations
C.F. Peters (Firm)--Correspondence.
Subjects
Composers--United States.; Music--Manuscripts.
Form/Genre
Clippings (Information artifacts); Contracts.; Correspondence.; Photographic prints.; Programs (Documents); Scrapbooks.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift, George Crumb, 2011.
Accruals
Further accruals are expected.
Related Material
The following Library of Congress Music Division collections contain correspondence or music by Crumb:
Nicolas Slonimsky Collection (ML31.S6)
Martha Graham Collection (ML31.G727)
and the
Moldenhaur Archives at the Library of Congress (ML31.M6)
. Crumb's holograph score for Ancient Voices of Children (ML29.c93 no.1 <case>) is in the Elizabeth Sprague Coolidge Foundation Collection. His score for Madrigals, Books 1-2 (ML30.3c.C79 no.1 <case>) is in the Serge Koussevitzky Music Foundation Collection.
Access and Restrictions
The George Crumb Papers are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Music Division prior to visiting in order to determine whether the desired materials will be available at that time.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1929, October 24 Born, Charleston, West Virginia, to musicians George Henry Crumb, Sr. and Vivian Crumb
circa 1939 Began composing works "somewhat in the style of Mozart"
1944-1947 Attended Charleston High School
1948-1950 Studied piano and composition at Mason College of Music, Charleston, W. Va.
1949, May 21 Married Elizabeth May Brown
1950 Daughter Elizabeth Ann Crumb born
1951-1952 Studied composition with Eugene Weigel at the University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign
1953-1959 Studied composition with Ross Lee Finney at the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor. Finney emphasized meticulous notation, a characteristic evident in Crumb's works. At Michigan, he was introduced to and inspired by the poetry of Federico García Lorca, whose texts become the source for many future compositions
1955-1956 Studied composition with Boris Blacher at the Berlin Hochschule für Musik on a Fulbright grant
1959 Doctorate, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor. His dissertational submission, Variazioni, is not premiered until 1965 Taught piano and composition, University of Colorado, Boulder Met pianist David Burge and composed Five Pieces for Piano, a work that earned Crumb widespread praise
1962 Son David Reed Crumb born
1964-1965 Began residency at the Buffalo Center for the Creative and Performing Arts
1965 Moved to Media, Pennsylvania Son Peter Stanley Crumb born Premiere of Madrigals, Books I-II, commissioned by the Serge Koussevitzky Music Foundation in the Library of Congress
1965-1997 Professor, composition, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Penn.
1967 Composed Echoes of Time and the River
1968 Received Pulitzer Prize for Echoes of Time and the River
1969, July 16-24 Composed Night of the Four Moons, a work inspired by the Apollo 11 space flight
1969 Completed Songs, Drones, and Refrains of Death, his first Lorca-inspired work that had been started in 1962
1970, Oct. 23 Premiere of Black Angels by the Stanley Quartet at the University of Michigan
1970, Oct. 31 Premiere of Ancient Voices of Children at the 14th Coolidge Festival of Chamber Music. The piece was commissioned by the Elizabeth Sprague Coolidge Foundation in the Library of Congress
1972, Mar. 17 First performance of Vox Balaenae by the New York Camerata at the Library of Congress. The work contained masked performers and other theatrical elements similar to Lux Aeterna, composed the previous year
1972-1979 Composed Makrokosmos, a cycle of four works for amplified piano
1977, May 5 New York Philharmonic premiere of Star-Child under Pierre Boulez
1978 PBS broadcast of Robert Mugge's film, George Crumb: Voice of the Whale
1984, June 7 New York Philharmonic premiere of tone-poem A Haunted Landscape under Arthur Wiesberg
1986 Apr. Served as the American representative at the Conference of the Union of Soviet Composers
1988, Jan. 17 Zeitgeist is premiered at the Charles Ives Festival in Duisburg, Germany
1997 Composed Mundis Canis, a work inspired by the personalities of the Crumb family dogs.
1998 Mundis Canis premiered by guitarist David Starobin and Crumb himself on percussion
2000 Star-Child, recorded for the first time on Bridge Records' Complete Crumb Edition, won a Grammy Award for Best Contemporary Classical Composition
2002-2007 Composed the American Songbook, a cycle of six works for voice, percussion quartet, and amplified piano
2011, Apr. 28 Thomas Hampson performed selections from the American Songbook at the Library of Congress
Scope and Content Note
The George Crumb Papers span the period 1956 to 2011, with the majority of the materials dating from 1965 to 2003. The collection consists of holograph manuscript scores and sketches, correspondence and business papers, and a series of meticulously assembled scrapbooks chronicling Crumb's distinguished career as a composer.
The music materials represent works composed exclusively from 1959 to the present day, beginning with Crumb's Variazioni, his dissertational submission to the University of Michigan. They include inked score paste-ups for publication, pencil scores and sketches, drafts, annotated photo-reproductions, and several score transparencies. Crumb's final copy scores are inked with extraordinary precision and reflect the influence of his father's skills as a copyist and Ross Lee Finney's pedagogy. Most contain extensive patches of inked-over whiteout and pasted insertions. Notable scores include the Pulitzer Prize-winning Echoes of Time and the River, Ancient Voices of Children, Black Angels, Five Pieces for Piano, A Haunted Landscape, Lux Aeterna, Madrigals, Makrokosmos, Mundis Canis, Star-Child, and Vox Balaenae. Additionally, the collection includes several sketchbooks with materials to numerous compositions, currently identified only as volumes "A" through "C". A more comprehensive list of their contents will be available at a later time.
Business papers consist chiefly of letters, telegrams, contracts, programs, and other documents from 1956 to 2011. Included is university and publisher correspondence, student inquiries, and letters from various colleagues and friends, such as David Burge. The scrapbooks comprise seven custom bound volumes of clippings, programs, photographs, interviews, posters, and other materials that detail Crumb's musical accomplishments from roughly 1963 to 2001. These are assembled with the same meticulous care as the composer's scores and include hundreds of performance reviews from both American and international newspapers.
Organization of the George Crumb Papers
The George Crumb Papers are organized in three series:
Music, 1959-2003
Business Papers, 1956-2011
Scrapbooks, 1963-2001
http://lccn.loc.gov/2012562132
Container List
- Music, 1959-2003 (Box 1-10)
  Holograph manuscript scores and sketches, drafts, annotated scores, sketchbooks, and several transparencies. Final copy manuscripts contain inked-over whiteout and pasted insertions that may require special handling.
  Arranged alphabetically by title of work. Cross references are provided for components of multi-volume works with distinctive titles, namely Makrokosmos, Images, and American Songbook.
  - Instrumental
    - Black angels: Images I: thirteen images from the dark land: for electric string quartet, 1970
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 10/1)
      - Sketches (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Celestial mechanics: Makrokosmos IV: cosmic dances for amplified piano, four hands, 1979
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 10/2)
      - Holograph manuscript score (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Dream sequence: Images II: for violin, cello, piano, and percussion (and offstage "glass harmonica"), 1976
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 10/3)
      - Sketches (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Easter dawning: for carillon, 1991
      - Holograph manuscript score, Caption title: Easter bells (Box-folder 1/4)
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up, 1992 revised version (Box-folder 1/4)
      - Sketches and drafts, Both versions (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Echoes of time and the river: Echoes II: four processionals for orchestra, 1967
      - Sketches (Box-folder 1/6-8)
    - Eine kleine Mitternachtmusik (A little midnight music): ruminations on a tune of Thelonius Monk: for amplified piano, 2001
      - Sketches and drafts (Box-folder 2/1)
    - Eleven echoes of autumn: Echoes I: for violin, alto flute, clarinet, and piano, 1965
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 10/4)
      - Sketches and drafts (Box-folder 2/2)
    - Five pieces for piano, 1962
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 2/3)
    - Four nocturnes: Night music II: for violin and piano, 1964
      - 2 holograph manuscript score paste-ups (Box-folder 2/4)
      - Printed holograph manuscript score transparency (Box-folder 2/5)
      - Photocopied holograph manuscript score, Annotations and corrections (Box-folder 2/6)
      - Sketches and drafts (Box-folder 2/6)
    - Gnomic variations: for piano, 1981
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 2/7)
      - Holograph manuscript score, Cover title: Fantasy variations (Box-folder 2/7)
      - Sketches (Box-folder 2/8)
    - A haunted landscape: for orchestra, 1984
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 2/9)
      - Photocopied holograph manuscript score, Annotations and corrections (Box-folder 2/10)
      - Sketches (Box-folder 3/1-3)
    - An idyll for the misbegotten: amplified piano and percussion, 3 players, 1986
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 3/4)
      - Sketches and drafts (Box-folder 3/5)
    - Images I see Black angels
    - Images II see Dream sequence
    - A little suite for Christmas: A.D. 1979: for piano, 1980
      - 2 holograph manuscript score paste-ups (Box-folder 3/6-7)
      - Sketches (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Makrokosmos I: twelve fantasy-pieces after the Zodiac: for amplified piano, 1972
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 3/8)
      - Sketches (Box-folder 3/9)
    - Makrokosmos II: twelve fantasy-pieces after the Zodiac: for amplified piano, 1973
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 4/1)
      - Sketches (Box-folder 4/2)
    - Makrokosmos III see Music for a summer evening
    - Makrokosmos IV see Celestial mechanics
    - Mundus canis (A dog's world): five humoresques for guitar and percussion (one player), 1997
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 4/3)
      - Sketches and drafts (Box-folder 4/3)
    - Music for a summer evening: Makrokosmos III: for two amplified pianos and percussion (two players), 1974
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 10/5)
    - Night music II see Four nocturnes
    - Otherworldly resonances: six tableaux for two amplified pianos, book II, 2002
      - 2 holograph manuscript score paste-ups, Original version (Box-folder 4/4-5)
      - Sketches, 3 movement version (Box-folder 4/6)
    - Pastoral drone: for organ, 1982
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 4/7)
    - Processional (piano), 1983
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 4/8)
      - Sketches (Box-folder 4/8)
    - Quest: for guitar, soprano saxophone, harp, contrabass, and percussion (two players), 1990
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 4/9)
      - Sketches (Box-folder 4/10)
    - Variazioni: for large orchestra, 1959
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 4/11)
      - 2 photocopied holograph manuscript score paste-ups (Box-folder 5/1-3)
    - Vox balaenae (Voice of the whale): for three masked players: electric flute, electric cello, electric piano, 1971
      - Sketches (Box-folder 5/4)
    - Zeitgeist: six tableaux for two amplified pianos, book I, 1987
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 5/5)
      - Sketches (Box-folder 5/6)
  - Vocal
    - American songbook, 2002-2007, see I. The river of life; see II. A journey beyond time; see III. Unto the hills
    - Ancient voices of children: for soprano, boy soprano, oboe, mandolin, harp, electric piano (and toy piano), and percussion (three players), 1970, Commissioned by the Elizabeth Sprague Coolidge Foundation in the Library of Congress
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up, Laid in: photocopied score and sketches; see ML29.C93 no.1 <case>
    - Apparition: elegiac songs and vocalises for soprano and amplified piano (on texts from Walt Whitman's "When lilacs last in the dooryard bloom'd"), 1979
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 5/7)
      - Holograph manuscript score (Box-folder 5/8)
      - Sketches (Box-folder 5/9)
    - Federico's little songs for children: for soprano, flute (also piccolo, alto flute, and bass flute), and harp, 1986
      - Holograph manuscript score (Box-folder 5/10)
      - Photocopied holograph manuscript score, Annotations and corrections (Box-folder 5/11)
      - Sketches and drafts (Box-folder 5/11)
    - A journey beyond time: American songbook II: songs of despair and hope: a cycle of Afro-American spirituals for voice, percussion quartet, and amplified piano, 2003
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 6/1)
    - Lux aeterna: for five masked musicians (soprano, bass flute (and soprano recorder), sitar, and two percussionists), 1971
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 6/2)
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up, On envelope: Not for printer (Box-folder 6/3)
      - Sketches (Box-folder 6/4)
    - Madrigals (soprano, various instruments), 1965-1969
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 6/5)
      - Photocopied holograph manuscript score, Annotations and corrections (Box-folder 6/6)
      - Performance instructions paste-up (Box-folder 6/7)
      - 2 holograph manuscript scores, Books I and II only (2 scores each); Laid in: photocopied scores and transparencies; Commissioned by the Serge Koussevitzky Music Foundation in the Library of Congress; see ML30.3c.C79 no.1 <case>
      - Sketches (Box-folder 6/8)
    - Night music I: for soprano, piano (and celesta), and percussion (two players), 1963
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 7/1)
      - Printed holograph manuscript score transparency (Box-folder 7/2)
      - Sketches (Box-folder 7/3-4)
    - Night of the four moons: for alto, alto flute (doubling piccolo), banjo, electric cello, and percussion (one player), 1969
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 10/6)
      - Sketches (Box-folder 7/5)
    - The river of life: American songbook I: songs of joy and sorrow: a cycle of hymns, spirituals, and revival tunes for voice, percussion quartet, and amplified piano, 2003
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 7/6)
    - The sleeper: for mezzo-soprano and piano, 1984
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 7/7)
      - Sketches and drafts (Box-folder 7/7)
    - Songs, drones, and refrains of death: a cycle of poems by Federico García Lorca: for baritone, electric guitar, electric contrabass, electric piano (and electric harpsichord), and percussion (two players), 1968
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 10/7)
      - Sketches (Box-folder 7/8-9)
    - Star-child: a parable for soprano, antiphonal children's voices, male speaking choir (and bell ringers), and large orchestra, 1977
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 10/8)
      - Sketches (Box-folder 8/1-2)
    - Unto the hills: American songbook III: songs of sadness, yearning, and innocence: a cycle of Appalachian folk songs for voice, percussion quartet, and amplified piano, 2002
      - Holograph manuscript score paste-up (Box-folder 8/3)
  - Sketchbooks
    - Sketchbook "A", undated (Box 9)
    - Sketchbook "B", undated (Box 9)
    - Sketchbook "C", undated (Box 9)
- Business Papers, 1956-2011 (Box 11-28)
  Letters, telegrams, contracts, programs, royalty statements, itineraries, and other documents. Correspondence from publishers (mostly C.F. Peters), collegiate staff, and students is heavily represented. Also included are letters from various colleagues and friends, such as David Burge.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1956-1966 (Box-folder 11/1-10)
  - 1967-1969 March (Box-folder 12/1-9)
  - 1969 April-1971 (Box-folder 13/1-11)
  - 1972-1973 (Box-folder 14/1-8)
  - 1974-1976 March (Box-folder 15/1-9)
  - 1976 April-1978 June (Box-folder 16/1-9)
  - 1978 July-1980 September (Box-folder 17/1-9)
  - 1980 October-1983 June (Box-folder 18/1-11)
  - 1983 July-1985 June (Box-folder 19/1-8)
  - 1985 July-1987 (Box-folder 20/1-10)
  - 1988-1990 (Box-folder 21/1-12)
  - 1991-1995 March (Box-folder 22/1-17)
  - 1995 April-1998 June (Box-folder 23/1-13)
  - 1998 July-2001 March (Box-folder 24/1-11)
  - 2001 April-2004 September (Box-folder 25/1-14)
  - 2004-October 2007 (Box-folder 26/1-13)
  - 2008-2010 June (Box-folder 27/1-10)
  - 2010 July-2011 April (Box-folder 28/1-3)
- Scrapbooks, 1963-2001 (Box 29-35)
  Meticulously assembled volumes of clippings, programs, photographs, and other materials.
  Arranged numerically by volume number. Volumes are roughly chronological in content order, but may contain miscellaneous items within several years of the dates specified.
  - Volume I: 1963-1973 (Box 29)
  - Volume II: 1973-1978 (Box 30)
  - Volume III: 1978-1984 (Box 31)
  - Volume IV: 1984-1989 (Box 32)
  - Volume V: 1989-1997 (Box 33)
  - Volume VI: 1997-2000 (Box 34)
  - Volume VII: 2000-2001 (Box 35)